<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="pers" xml:lang="en" xml:id="PRS3911Eusebius">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eusebius</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Prosopography of the Ethiopian and Eritrean written tradition</p>
            <p>A TEI file converted from the ETHIO-authority
                                                  google spreadsheet</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language></langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-04-28">batch updated according to requirements and issues.</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-03-21"> Created file from
                                                  google spreadsheet </change>
         <change who="ES" when="2016-02-09">CREATED: person</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person sex="1">
               <persName xml:id="n1" xml:lang="gez">አውሳብዮስ፡ </persName>
               <persName type="normalized" corresp="#n1">ʾAwsābyos</persName>
               <persName type="main" corresp="#n1" xml:lang="en">Eusebius </persName>
               <persName xml:id="n2" xml:lang="gez">አውስብዮስ፡ </persName>
               <persName type="normalized" corresp="#n2">ʾAwsǝbyos</persName>
               <occupation> martyr, son of Basilides, commemorated on <date type="diesNatalis">23 Yakkātit</date></occupation>
               <floruit>Vita copied from the Synaxary for 23 Yakkātit (as translated by Budge): On this day became a martyr Saint Eusebius, the son of the holy and blessed Basilides, the
                  captain of the royal troops of the city of Antioch, and the father of kings. And this saint
                  was in the war against the men of the country of the Persians, and when Diocletian denied
                  our Lord Jesus Christ, Basilides sent to this son Eusebius, and told him that Diocletian had
                  denied Christ. And this saint summoned his kinsfolk, the saints and men of the palace, that
                  is to say, ‘Abadir, and Justus, and Claudius, and Theodore from the East, and he told them
                  how Diocletian had denied our Lord Christ, and how he worshipped idols; and they were
                  exceedingly sorry. And the holy and excellent man Eusebius said unto them, “I want to
                  shed my blood for the Name of Christ,” and all those saints agreed with him in this
                  excellent decision, and they swore each to the other that they would do so. And when the
                  Romans had conquered their enemies, and had returned to the city of Antioch with victory
                  and joy, Diocletian and his soldiers went out and met them, and Khermanos (Romanus),
                  the father of Victor, advised the emperor to have the saints brought before him, and to
                  fetch idols for them to worship. And the emperor did as Khermanos (Romanus) advised
                  him, and he summoned the saints to him, and said unto them, “Ye know well that I love
                  you exceedingly, I want you to make my heart to rejoice, and to worship Apollo.” And
                  when Saint Eusebius heard this he was exceedingly angry, and he drew his sword and
                  wished to kill the emperor, and the emperor fled from him and hid himself. But this saint
                  killed many of the emperor’s companions, and had it not been that Basilides restrained his
                  son and his kinsmen the saints, they would have hilled all the emperor’s soldiers. After
                  this Khermanos (Romanus) advised the emperor to send Eusebius to the country of Egypt,
                  and to let the officers kill him there, [saying], “If he remaineth here in this city he will stir
                  up the men of the city against thee at all times, and thou wilt not be able to do anything
                  when thou wishest.” And the emperor wrote and commanded [the governor] to send
                  Eusebius to the country of Egypt, to Lolyanos, the governor of Keft (Coptos), and he sent
                  him away as the emperor commanded. And when Eusebius arrived in Keft (Coptos), the
                  governor tortured him very severely on the wheel, and he cut off his members, and after
                  this he beat him severely, and after this he boiled him in a cauldron. And our Lord sent to him His angel, who strengthened him under his tribulation, and comforted him, and healed
                  his wounds, and raised him up whole and uninjured. And then the angel caught away his
                  soul to the Garden of Delight, and the saint saw the abode of the martyrs, and the saints,
                  and the righteous, and he saw the places which God had prepared for him, and his father,
                  and his brother, and his kinsfolk, and his soul rejoiced exceedingly. And after this the
                  governor commanded the soldiers to burn him in a furnace outside the city of ‘Ehnasa, and
                  they burnt him as the governor had commanded them; and the angel of God came down to
                  him in the red-hot furnace, and made the flame to be as cold as ice, and he brought Saint
                  Eusebius out of the fiery furnace whole and uninjured. And the officers and the judges
                  advised the governor, saying, “O governor, command the soldiers to cut off the head of
                  this man, and have rest from him”; and the emperor commanded and the soldiers cut off
                  the head of this Eusebius with the sword, and he received the crown of martyrdom in the
                  kingdom of the heavens. Salutation to Eusebius, the son of Basilides, the general.</floruit>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>